A Guide to the Richard F. Bohn Civil War Letters 1862-1865
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
{Special Collections, University of Virginia Library}
Richard F. Bohn Civil War Letters 1862-1865
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11409
24 items
Union Soldier Richard F. Bohn writes from the battlefields of Virginia, primarily from a camp near Petersburg, to his parents and sister. Bohn describes his journey to the front; construction of forts and rifle pits at Petersburg; camp life; picket duty; several engagements including Fort Stedman and the fall of Petersburg and Richmond. There are references to the election of 1864; black soldiers; the drunkeness of Captain Franklin Schmehl; the hanging of two deserteres; and his colonel Joseph Ard Matthews. The collection also contains an 1862 letter from Ella Corbin to her brother Miner H. Corbin of the 22nd Connecticut; and an 1863 letter from William Heafer of the 167th Pennsylvania to Elbina F. Bohn.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: Charles Apfelbaum Rare Manuscripts & Archives, Watchung, N.J., July 3, 1998
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of 24 items, 1862-1865, mostly Civil War letters of Private Richard F. Bohn, Company H, 205th Pennsylvania Infantry Regiment, while stationed at the Petersburg front in Virginia, to his parents, sister and family. He enlisted on September 2, 1864 and was mustered out with his company on June 2, 1865.¹ Also present are single letters of Ella Corbin to her brother, Private Miner H. Corbin, Company G, 22nd Connecticut Infantry Regiment (November 12, 1862) and William Hofer, Company D, 167th Pennsylvania Infantry Regiment, to an unidentified correspondent, Feburary 14, 1863.
Bohn's letters, written mostly from various camps and towns in Virginia (Suffolk, Petersburg, Dutch Gap and Burkeville), discusses his impressions of the war, his comrades and commanding officers, personal and public incidents, camp news, battle and march rumors, and family news. He lists the names of his parents, siblings and relatives in several letters (October 16, 1864, January 15 and April 11, 1865). Military life and activities described include the transport of Bohn's regiment to Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, Camp Curtin, Baltimore and Washington, D.C. (September 6, 1864), camp life during the Petersburg siege, including construction of forts and rifle pits (October 7 and 16, 1864), night drills (October 11, 1864), a dinner of soup and hardtack, bread loaves issued to soldiers (October 16, 1864), winter quarters (October 26, 1864), a graphic description of the capture and butchering of cattle (1864), the execution of two deserters of the 187th New York Infantry who had joined the Confederate army (December 16, 1864), soldiers' and officers' drunkenness (October 26 and October ? 1864), soldiers' support of Democratic presidential candidate General George B. McClellan (October 16 and 26 and ante November 8, 1864), the capture of various soldiers (October 30, November 24, 1864), the capture of stationery and tobacco from dead rebel soldiers (April 1, 1865), the dramatic escape of a Union soldier from Confederate soldiers (October 30, 1864), and Bohn's enjoyment of soldiering and his five-year reenlistment (February 15, 1865). Another of his letters, October 30, 1864, is written on U. S. Christian Commission stationery.
Battles and engagements described include: Burgess Mill/Boydton Plank Road (October 30, 1864), Fort Stedman (April 1, 1865), and the capture of Petersburg and Richmond (April 11, 1865).
Among the soldiers and officers of the 205th Pennsylvania mentioned or referred by name: Captain Richard Boone (October 16 and ante November 8, 1864), Privates Elias D. Hoch, John H. Roth and Darling Meadler (April 11, 1865), Colonel Joseph Ard Matthews (March 4, 1865), First Lieutenant David B. Roberts and Second Lieutenant Irwin S. Phillips (April 11, 1865), Captain Franklin Schmehl (October 26 and October ?, 1864), and Colonel William F. Walters (October ?, 1864); Bohn also reports the capture of Colonel [Tobias Kauffman], 209th Pennsylvania Infantry (November 24, 1864).
Regiments other than the 205th Pennsylvania mentioned in these letters include: the 22nd Connecticut Infantry Regiment (November 12, 1862), the Ulster Guards, 20th Regiment New York State Militia (September 6, 1864; commanded by Colonel George W. Pratt), 187th New York Infantry (December 16, 1864), the167th Pennsylvania Infantry Regiment (February 14, 1863), the 205th, 207th, and 211th Pennsylvania (October ?, 1864), the 200th, 205th, 207th, 208th, 209th, 211th Pennsylvania Regiments, and the 2nd Pennsylvania Heavy Artillery (November 24, 1864).
There are several references, mostly derogatory, to African-Americans: the presence of 400 blacks at Camp Curtin (September 6, 1864), "we are working like niggars" (October 7, 1864), officers make "make a fellow work like a Negro" and Bohn's obtaining lodging in a black family's shanty after becoming lost (October 16, 1864), and the presence of black soldiers and arrest of a black Union soldier for killing a Confederate soldier (November 24, 1864).
A few letters are written by or refer to members of the Heafer family (Bohn's in-laws): William Heafer, writing from Suffolk, Virginia, includes a love poem to Elbina F. Bohn (February 14, 1863), William's visit with the 205th Pennsylvania (October 16, 1864) and Richard Bohn's mention of him to his sister Elbina (1864), and passing mention of Jacob Heafer (November 24, 1864).
¹Samuel P. Bates, History of the Pennsylvania Volunteers, 1861-5(Harrisburg: B. Singerly, State Printer, 1870), 5:650.
Contents List
- Letter [1862 Nov. 12] (Box 1)
  Ella Corbin, Washington, D.C., pencilled letter, "Wed. Morn 12th," to "(Mine) Dear brother," Mr. Miner H. Corbin, Company G, 22nd Regiment Connecticut: "We have sad news from Byron. As L___ goes this morning, hastily I pack a little box for you. Much love from all. Be of good cheer. Your sister Ella. Trust in God!" On verso is a book agent's advertisement card, "Conditions for Headley's Life of Washington."
  Private Miner H. Corbin of Union, Connecticut, enlisted into Company G of the 22nd Connecticut Regiment on September 5, 1862 and was honorably discharged July 7, 1863. Connecticut Adjutant General's Office, Catalogue of Connecticut Volunteer Organizations, With Additional Enlistments and Casualties to July 1, 1864, Compiled From Records in the Adjutant General's Office, and Published by Order of the Legislature, Horace J. Morse, Adjutant-General(Hartford: Press of Case, Lockwood and Company, 1864), 682; Joel Tyler Headley, Illustrated Life of Washington, With Vivid Pen Paintings of Battles and Incidents of the Revolution(New York: G. & F. Bill, 1859).
- Letter 1863 Feb. 14 (Box 1)
  William Heafer, Suffolk, Virginia, to "Dear Sir": discusses the building of three forts; identifies himself as a member of Company D, 167th Regiment Pennsylvania, Peck's Division [Major General John James Peck, 1821-1878]; postscript is addressed to Elbina F. Bohn asking her to write and includes poem "if you love me as I love love you no [knife] can cut us in two"
  Heafer is identified as "William Hofer" in Bates, History of the Pennsylvania Volunteers, 4:1123 and as Sergeant William L. Heafer, Company H, 205th Pennsylvania, 5:649.
- Letter 1864 Sept. 6 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, Washington, to "My Dear father mother": written on read and blue bordered stationery of the "Ulster Guards, 20th Regiment New York State Militia, Colonel George W. Pratt, Commanding"; discusses transport of his regiment by rail to Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, Camp Curtin, and Baltimore (where he saw three to four hundred blacks) before arriving in Washington and bivouacked at Soldiers' Rest; 1200 men in the regiment.
- Letter 1864 Sept. 27 (Box 1)
  [Unidentified], "Camp Near Front of Petersburg," to "My Dear love Elbina Bohn": hopes to send his photograph; mentions her brother's (Richard Bohn?) letter; recalls their courtship and promises to haul her carriage from Saturday to Sunday; asks for her photograph; remainder of letter is missing.
- Letter 1864 Oct. 7 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Near Front of Petersburg," to "My Dear Parents": his regiment has worked at forts and constructed rifle pits for three days and "we are working like niggars"; pickets are firing at rebels as he writes this; bushwhackers are harassing them; mentions having received letters from Elizabeth Clay and Eliza Fisher; remainder of letter is missing.
- Letter 1864 Oct. 11 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Near Petersburg," to "My Dear Parents": complains they have not written to him; regiment's colonel took them out for a night drill; effects of the shelling at Petersburg.
- Letter 1864 Oct. 16 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Near Petersburg," to "My Dear Parents": building a fort, rifle pits and batteries; officers make "make a fellow work like a negro;" caught lazing and napping instead of chopping wood by an officer he calls "old Rich" (Captain Richard Boone?); describes a dinner of soup and hardtack; soldiers issued a loaf of bread; tells his sister Elbina that William Heafer visited the company; nothing here but sandy bottom and wilderness; postscript to his brother requests gloves, envelopes, stamps; lists the names of his brothers and sisters and adds a postscript "hurra McClennen" (general and presidential candidate George B. McClellan, 1826-1885)
- Letter 1864 Oct. 17? (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Near front": has received his father's letter of the 16th; is on picket duty 8 hours daily; includes "Soldiers hymn For My Mother"--"... Alone I Lay Angels watching over me mother till the Breaking of the Day... ," a jumble of sentiments of home, religion and fond memories of his mother and family; asks his sister to write and tell him where his brother Nathan is stationed; while on picket duty he is sitting on "a nice piece of wood" writing this letter.
- Letter 1864 Oct. 26 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Near Front Petersburg," to "My Dear Parents": the soldiers are building winter quarters; Democrats in camp favor McClellan for president; requests gloves and envelopes; a drunken soldier vomited into the cookhouse at City Point; claims Captain Franklin Schmehl is drunk nearly all the time.
- Letter 1864 Oct. 30 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Near Front Petersburg," to "My Dear Parents," on U. S. Christian Commission stationery: describes fighting on the 27th (engagement at Burgess' Mill or Boydton Plank Road) and the dramatic escape of a Union soldier briefly captured by the rebels; thanks his father for sending two dollars and asks for a pair of gloves; is writing this letter on his knapsack while lying on his belly.
- Letter [1864 Oct. ?] (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, Petersburg, to his brother]: [first page of letter is missing; begins "and i got the Receive of the Box and 16 post stamps"]; Colonel William F. Walters is the brigade commander (2nd Brigade, 3rd Division) and commands three Pennsylvania regiments (the 205th, 207th, and 211th); accuses Captain Franklin Schmehl of drunkenness; troops are so close to Petersburg that its church steeples can be seen.
- Letter ante 1864 Nov. 8 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn to his sister?: letter is incomplete, missing pages?; begins "Letter/Always When i Came to the Camp Last night they Said that they were some Letters here for me.. ."; had to go to Captain Richard Boone of Company E in order to get his sister's letter, and when he saw it he exclaimed, "hurrah for Bern Township girls I near throat [threw] my old shelter tent Down"; tells his brother of a Pittsburgh band, "they Play so good"; regimental drills during the evenings; a camp preacher prays for them; mentions a cousin James Adams; "yes i would [wish] war over father but every thing is Democratic here in our Army they holler like hell for [McClellan]."
- Letter 1864 Nov. 24 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Near Dutch Gap," to "My Dear Parents": today is his birthday (but does not state his age); mentions a Jacob Heafer and asks him to write; discusses the presence of black soldiers and describes an incident during which a black Union soldier was arrested for shooting dead a Confederate soldier who was chopping wood; Pennsylvania infantry regiments nearby include the 200th, 205th, 207th, 208th, 209th, 211th, and the 2nd Pennsylvania Heavy Artillery; description of the capture of the 209th's colonel by the rebels who stripped him of his clothing and made him walk barefooted [Colonel Tobias Kauffman was captured at Bermuda Hundred on November 17, 1864]; "we was shelling the Rebels like hell"; gives his mailing address as "Richard F. Bohn, Co. H, 205th (Pennsylvania) Regiment, Washington, D. C., Camp near City Point, Virginia, care of Captain Schmehl."
  Bates, History of the Pennsylvania Volunteers, 5:710, 712
- Letter 1864 Dec. 16 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Front Petersburg," to "My Dear Parents": hard marching in heavy snow and rain to Stony Creek Station near the Blackwater River, he became separated from his regiment (during which he found lodging in a black family's shanty); detailed description of the execution by hanging of two deserters (Edward Row and Daniel Smith, 187th New York Infantry) who had joined and fought for the Confederate army until their capture by General "Sherman" in the Shenandoah Valley [Bohn means General Philip A. Sheridan, 1831-1888].
- Letter 1864 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Near Front Petersburg," to "My Dear Lovely Parents": graphic description of the capture and butchering of cattle: "us felled him with our knives and Cut his head off and then we skinned him he was fat we judge about 500 lbs he weight and the skin we [threw] in the water and the guts and... the heart we took and the Liver and then we Cut him up in quarters"; has received a letter from his brother Nathan stating that he had nearly drowned at Middletown; RFB reminds his sister to take care of herself "you know for what till he Comes home W. H." [William L. Heafer?].
- Letter [1864] (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn's address in case his family wishes to telegraph him: "Mr. Richard F. Bohn Co H 205th Regt P[ennsylvania] V[olunteers] 2th Brigade 3 Division 9th Army [Corps] Camp from S. Petersburg via"; on verso "here is some tobacco for you Brother/R. Bohn."
- Letter [1864] (Box 1)
  Mailing address label, "Mr. Richard F. Bohn, Co. H 205th Regt P[ennsylvania] V[olunteers] Washington, D. E. Camp Near City Point Via in Care of Capt [Schmehl], Box Direction, W. B./R. B."
- Letter 1865 Jan. 15 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Front Petersburg," to "My Dear Sister": has written to his cousin Hetty Adams and a song "Prairie Flowers"; says he is "going to make hay" in Petersburg and Richmond; mentions family acquaintances; last page of letter lists several Bohn family members.
- Letter 1865 Feb. 15 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Near Petersburg," to "My Dear Sir," w/envelope (William Bohn, Berks County, Pennsylvania, in care of Elias Reben [Reuben?]): bottom third section of this letter is missing; is in good health; mentions Reuben; enjoys soldiering and hopes to enlist for five more years.
- Letter 1865 Mar. 4 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Front Petersburg," to "My Dear Parents": comments on Elbina's [his sister] son who weights 10 and a half pounds; soldiers were paid March 2 and he sent his father a $50 banknote; praises his colonel [Joseph Ard Matthews, later a brevet brigadier general, ?-1872] as the best in the whole army because "he reported our Regt Condempt and they can't put us in a fight if our Regt is Condempt--Condempt is youse no not fit to go in a fight"; lists several members of the Bohn family.
- Letter 1865 Mar. 11 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Front Petersburg," to "My Dear Parents": is concerned they have not received the $50 banknote he mailed; regrets the drafting of his cousins by the army; asks to be remembered to a Elizabeth Clay; promises to catch a muskrat.
- Letter 1865 Mar. 19 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Front Petersburg," to "My Dear Sister": expects a hard fight soon because headquarters has been moved; jokes about sending her son (his nephew) to the Petersburg front so that he may drill him as a soldier if he continues to misbehave.
- Letter 1865 April 1 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp Front Petersburg," to "My Dear Parents": describes his participation in the battle of Fort Stedman (March 25, 1865); he captured 50 sheets of paper, 40 envelopes and tobacco from dead rebel soldiers.
- Letter 1865 April 1 (Box 1)
  Richard F. Bohn, "Camp at Berksville [Burkeville] South," to "My Dear Parents": had fought two battles on April 2; announces the capture of Petersburg and Richmond; describes the wounding (John H. Roth and Darling Meadler) and deaths of various comrades including Elias D. Hoch and First Lieutenant David B. Roberts; wounding of [Second Lieutenant Irwin S. Phillips]; has heard rumors of Confederate General Robert E. Lee's (1807-1870) surrender but says "they are fighting hard out about 14 miles from us"; lists several members of the Bohn family.
  Bates, History of the Pennsylvania Volunteers, 5:649-51.